{"tossups": [{"question": "An employee of this company, Conrad Ahlers, was illegally arrested at the behest of the German consulate while vacationing in Madrid. Rudolf Augstein was the owner of this company when it conducted research into the preparedness of military forces during a NATO exercise. Information gathered by this company exposed the Flick Scandal. Franz Josef Strauss jailed several employees of this company in a scandal that rocked Konrad Adenauer\u2019s government in 1962. For the point, name this German weekly news magazine.", "answer": "Der<b> Spiegel</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "This man claimed that the \u201cFreedom Club\u201d was responsible for his works, including a document sent to the<em> Washington Post</em> outlining his concern with modernization. This author of<em> Industrial Society and</em> <em>Its Future</em> resigned his math professorship at UC Berkeley at age 26. In 1996, this man was found by authorities in a log cabin in Montana. Three people were killed via mailed pipebombs by, for the point, what domestic terrorist whose nickname refers to his targets, universities and airports?", "answer": "Theodore John \u201cTed\u201d<b> Kaczynski</b> (accept the<b> Unabomber</b>)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "This dynasty refused to pay a ransom to Esen Taishi after he had captured the emperor Zhengtong in the Tumu Crisis. This dynasty ended after a coup in which its final emperor hung himself from a tree outside a palace built by the Yongle Emperor; in that coup, Li Zicheng established the short-lived Shun dynasty. A gira\u21b5e from Malindi was brought back to this dynasty during the voyages of Zheng He. For the point, name this dynasty that was shortly followed by the Qing [ching] and is known for trading porcelain ceramics with the West.", "answer": "<b> Ming</b> Dynasty", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "At age 12, this figure led an informant group called the Monkey Brigade. This figure\u2019s government charged George Fernandes with attempting to blow up government buildings in the Baroda Dynamite Case. This politician used a slogan translating to \u201cAbolish poverty, rescue the country.\u201d Pokhran-I [poke-ran \u201cone\u201d] was a successful nuclear test under this leader, who was assassinated in retaliation for Operation Blue Star by her Sikh bodyguards. For the point, name this first female Prime Minister of India.", "answer": "<b> I</b>ndira Priyadarshini<b> Gandhi</b> (prompt on Gandhi alone)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "Fort Blunder was accidentally built along the shore of this body of water, but in the wrong country. A battle on this body of water resulted in the loss of the<em> Spitfire</em> and took place near Valcour Island. Thomas MacDonough repelled the British from this lake in 1814. Its Fort Crown Point was used as the staging ground for Benedict Arnold and Ethan Allen\u2019s Green Mountain Boys to attack another stronghold here. The city of Plattsburgh and Fort Ticonderoga lie on the shores of, for the point, what large lake on the border of New York and Vermont?", "answer": "Lake<b> Champlain</b> Page 2", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "A character in this series is o\u21b5ered a choice of punishments between castration and having part of his right foot chopped o\u21b5; that character names his daughter after a word meaning \u201cstay put\u201d in the Mandinka language. A man in this series gains the nickname \u201cChicken George\u201d because of his prowess in training chickens for cockfighting. Near the start of this series, a brutal whipping is administered to Kunta Kinte when he refuses to accept the name Toby. For the point, name this landmark TV miniseries chronicling the origins of Alex Haley.", "answer": "<b> Roots</b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "This ruler never repaid a series of loans to Poland known as the Neapolitan Sums. During his reign, a group of Muslim converts called the Moriscos revolted during the War of the Alpujarras. Pope Sixtus V encouraged this man to send his navy, under the command of the Duke of Medina Sidonia, into an invasion where it was targeted by fireships during the Battle of Gravelines [grav-uh-leen]. For the point, name this husband of Bloody Mary, a king who ordered the Spanish Armada to attack England.", "answer": "<b> Philip II</b> of Spain", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "A political machine led by this man was originally named the Holy Alliance. This man\u2019s nomination as Minister to Great Britain was blocked by a vengeful John Calhoun. This man\u2019s wealthy background was attacked during a presidential bid by Charles Ogle in the Gold Spoon Oration. Before becoming president, this man led the Albany Regency, and, while president, he struggled to fight poor economic conditions in the aftermath of the Panic of 1837. For the point, name this presidential successor of Andrew Jackson.", "answer": "Martin<b> Van Buren</b> Page 3", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "One painting by this artist depicts a group of huddled, weary pilgrims heading to San Isidro. Another painting in the same collection by this artist depicts two men fighting each other with cudgels. This court painter of Charles IV depicted men on horseback stampeding through crowds of citizens in his painting <em>The Charge of the Mamelukes</em>. This artist paired that painting with one depicting a man in white with outstretched arms about to be shot. For the point, name this artist of<em> The Black Paintings</em> who depicted French troops executing the defenders of Madrid in<em> Third of May, 1808</em>.", "answer": "Francisco Jos\u00b4e de<b> Goya</b> y Lucientes", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "In November 2015, this man released the multilingual rock album<em> Wake</em> <em>Up!</em> In December 2015, this man and Patriarch Kirill issued the Havana declaration, calling for the end of religious persecution in the Middle East. This man canonized two of his predecessors, John XXIII [23] and John Paul II, and his immediate predecessor, Benedict XVI [16], resigned. For the point, name this current head of the Roman Catholic Church.", "answer": "Pope<b> Francis</b> (or Jorge<b> Bergoglio</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This leader canceled the Treaty of Hudaybiyyah after the allied Banu Khuza\u2019a people were attacked. Even though this man appointed his successor at the pond of Khumm, this man\u2019s death prompted the Ridda Wars. In one battle, Salman Farsi advised this man to dig a trench to prevent the Quraysh tribe from capturing Medina. This winner of the Battle of Badr conquered Mecca, his birth city, in 630, two years before his farewell<em> hajj</em>. For the point, name this prophet of Islam.", "answer": "<b> Muhammad</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Giovani Tolosani attempted to refute this scientist\u2019s theory by saying he developed it and looking for evidence later. An abstract containing this scientist\u2019s theory was published by his student Georg Rheticus in<em> Narratio Prima</em>. To avoid controversy, this thinker claimed that his theory was meant only to aid in mathematical calculations and was not necessarily true. This astronomer waited until just before his death to allow the publication of<em> On the Revolutions of the Celestial Spheres</em>. For the point, name this Polish astronomer who advanced a heliocentric model of the solar system.", "answer": "Nicolaus<b> Copernicus</b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {}, {"question": "A defender of this city refused to surrender to rule in Mistra before noting that \u201c[it] is fallen and I am still alive.\u201d Baldwin IX was coronated in this city one year before Kaloyan captured him. A sack of this city prompted the creations of the despotates of Morea and Epirus, as well as the Empire of Trebizond. After the siege of Zadar enriched Venice, Enrico Dandolo supported an attack on this city. A chain across the Golden Horn failed to stop Mehmed II from conquering, for the point, what capital of the Eastern Roman Empire?", "answer": "<b> Constantinople</b> (accept<b> Byzantium</b>; accept<b> Istanbul</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "To support an invasion of this region, underwater pipeline was laid in Operation Pluto and deception measures were taken in Operations Quicksilver and Fortitude South. Allied soldiers were often unable to maneuver due to hedgerows in this region. This region was considered an unlikely target because the Pas-de-Calais was closer. Artificial harbors called mulberries were used on Omaha and Gold Beaches in the invasion of, for the point, what French region invaded by the Allies in Operation Overlord on D-Day?", "answer": "<b> Normandy</b> (prompt on (Northern) France)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "These people were given ruinous forty-nine-year loans in order to allow them to purchase land. The Sudebnik of 1497 declared that these people were allowed to change allegiance during St. George\u2019s Day. These people either performed labor called<em> barshchina</em> or paid a rent called<em> obrok</em>. The freedom of these people and the Cossacks were the subject of Pugachev\u2019s Rebellion. For the point, name these poor Russian peasants who were bound to their land.", "answer": "Russian<b> serf</b>s (or<b> krepostnoi krestyanin</b>; prompt on (Russian) peasants; do not accept or prompt on slaves)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "R\u00b4omulo Gallegos was president of this country for nine months before being ousted by a coup in 1948, which put Marcos Jim\u00b4enez in power for ten years. Francisco de Miranda failed to earn the independence of this country, which was later won at the Battle of Carabobo. Shortages of common goods in this country have resulted in a black market for toilet paper. This country\u2019s wealth is primarily due to oil from its Lake Maracaibo. For the point, name this South American country, once led by Hugo Chavez from Caracas.", "answer": "<b> Venezuela</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "In an e\u21b5ort to maximize revenue, land in this kingdom was restricted from being given to the Church by the Statute of Mortmain. A period of civil war in this country known as the Anarchy ended with the conflict between Stephen and Empress Matilda and led to the reign of Henry II. It lost its territories of Anjou and Maine after the Battle of Bouvines [boo-veen]. This kingdom defeated Llewelyn the Last and William Wallace under the command of Edward Longshanks. For the point, name this kingdom ruled by Plantanagets like Richard the Lionheart.", "answer": "<b> England</b> (accept the<b> Angevin</b> Empire, do not accept or prompt on Great Britain or the United Kingdom)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A member of this movement, Johannes Bugenhagen, was called Doctor Pomeranus and crowned Christian III. The Count\u2019s Feud spread this movement in Denmark. Members of this movement condemned the execution of Michael Servetus. A leader of this movement wrote the<em> Institute</em> in Basel and passed the Ordinances of 1541 to make the city of Geneva a center of this movement. John Calvin was a member of, for the point, what movement that rejected the Catholic Church in Renaissance Europe?", "answer": "Protestant<b> Reformation</b> (accept anything related to the spread of<b> Protestant</b>ism in Europe) Page 6", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "Ruth Edna Kelley\u2019s first book is a detailed history about this tradition. An ad for Jello in a 1946 episode of the Baby Snooks Show helped popularize an aspect of this tradition that, in scattered regions of the Midwest and New England, takes place on \u201cBeggar\u2019s Night.\u201d The Gaels originally celebrated this event as Samhain, during which large bonfires were held. This event, which occurs two days before All Souls\u2019 Day, has much in common with Mexico\u2019s Day of the Dead. For the point, name this holiday whose traditional o\u21b5ering to souls has evolved into trick-or-treating.", "answer": "<b> Halloween</b> (accept<b> Allhalloween</b>; accept<b> All Hallow\u2019s Eve</b>; accept<b> All Saints\u2019 Eve</b>)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "This empire adopted a border defense force called the<em> limantei</em>. Auxiliary forces in this empire were grouped into<em> alae</em> [al-ee] and recruited from regional allies called socii [soke-ee-ee]. Its cavalry traditionally drew from the<em> equites</em> [ek-wee-tays] class and it separated its heavy infantry into<em> hastati</em>,<em> principes</em> [prin-key-pays], and<em> triarii</em>. Later fighting forces of this empire were comprised of ten cohorts and carried an eagle standard. For the point, name this ancient empire whose basic fighting unit, called a legion, defended the Italian peninsula.", "answer": "<b> Rome</b> (accept more specific answers like<b> Roman Empire</b> or<b> Roman Republic</b>) Page 7", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This organization minted brass coins whose value was backed by a guarantee to swap for an animal carcass. A representative of this organization, Robert Semple, was attacked during the Pemmican War in the Battle of Seven Oaks. The York Factory was an early center of this company, which was merged with the North West Company in 1821. Its first successful missions were sponsored by Prince Rupert after its 1670 founding, and it exists today as a retail brand. For the point, name this company, active in the fur trade, that is named for a prominent body of water in Canada.", "answer": "<b> Hudson</b>\u2019s<b> Bay Company</b> (or<b> HBC</b>) Page 8", "metadata": "History - American History"}], "bonuses": []}